Oliver Bonham-Carter

Curriculum Vitæ Updated: August 1, 2022

Dept of CS, Allegheny College, 520 North Main Street, Meadville, PA 16335 \boxtimes obonhamcarter @allegheny.edu http:// oliverbonhamcarter. Orcid: 0000-0001-9032-0398

Research Interests: To apply my education, research and other outlets of academic creativity to contribute to the development of better statistical methods to process, study and comprehend large-scale digital data. To develop better techniques of teaching and encouraging my students to follow in this exciting direction of research which will serve them in their careers as they build the world of tomorrow from today's

Work Experience

Assistant Professor, Allegheny College, Meadville, PA. 2017 - current Department of Computer Science

> 2016 Visiting Assistant Professor, Allegheny College, Meadville, PA. Department of Computer Science

2014 Fall - 2016 Management of Information Systems - Teaching, UNO, Omaha, Nebraska. CIST 2100: Organizations, Applications and Technology

2009 - 2016Bioinformatics - Research, Peter Kiewit Inst - UNO, Omaha, Nebraska. Post-translational modifications, protein interactions as a result of environmental stress, DNA gene prediction/detection using non-alignment, mathematically and statistically based ideas and methods

Teaching and Counseling, Aim for the Stars Math & Science Summer Camp, Omaha, Summers: 2007, 08, 09, 10 Nebraska.

Teaching: Robotics and Logics. Counseling: Zoology

2007 - 2009Mathematics - Teaching, UNO, Omaha, Nebraska. Mathematics Graduate Teaching Assistant; College Algebra and Intermediate Algebra

Mathematics - Teaching and Tutoring, UNO, Omaha, Nebraska. 2006 - 2007Teach and tutor mathematics at the study center at South High School

Summer 2006 Educator, Durham Western Heritage Museum, Omaha, Nebraska. Educator for the "Engineer-It!" attraction. Educator of youth summer camps for bridge & basic

structure building, as well as, basic engineering and design. General public relations for visitors of exhibit.

Collaborative Research Project, UNO/PKI & Omaha Zoo, Omaha, Nebraska. Spring 2006 Statistical software development for the Omaha Zoo.

Selected Publications

- March 2021 Oliver Bonham-Carter and Yee Mon Thu, "GenExSt: A Tool to Identify Correlation of Gene Expression after Normalization with Housekeeping Genes.", Future of Information and Communication Conference. Springer, Cham, 2021, https://github.com/developmentAC/genExSt.
 - April 2020 Enpu You, Oliver Bonham-Carter and Janyl Jumadinova, "Text mining in Python for Evaluating the Ethical Foundations in Computer Science", Poster featured at Pycon 2020, Python Software Foundation.

 Author details: https://us.pycon.org/2020/speaker/profile/992/, poster: https://us.pycon.org/2020/online/posters/
 - May 2020 **Janyl Jumadinova and Oliver Bonham-Carter**, "Integrating Ethics in Teaching Artificial Intelligence.", In the Proceedings of the 33rd International Artificial Intelligence Society Conference (poster), 2020. Conference gathering was cancelled due to the pandemic.
- March 2020 Oliver Bonham-Carter, "BeagleTM: An adaptable text mining method for relationship discovery in literature.", Future of Information and Communication Conference. Springer, Cham, 2020, https://github.com/developmentAC/beagleTM.
- Sept 2019 **Oliver Bonham-Carter and Yee Mon Thu**, "Systematic Normalization with Multiple Housekeeping Genes for the Discovery of Genetic Dependencies in Cancer.", CNB-MAC / ACMBCB2019, 2019.
- August 2016 **Oliver Bonham-Carter**, "Patterns and Signals of Biology: An Emphasis On The Role of Post Translational Modifications in Proteomes for Function and Evolutionary Progression.", Dissertation Thesis. University of Nebraska at Omaha, 2016.
- August 2016 Oliver Bonham-Carter and Dhundy Bastola, "PTM Tracker: A system for determining trends of PTM modification sites relative to protein domains.", The IEEE International Conference on Electro Information Technology (EIT), 2016.
- December 2015 Oliver Bonham-Carter, Ishwor Thapa, Steven From and Dhundy Bastola, "A study of bias and increasing organismal complexity from their post-translational modifications and reaction site interplays", Briefings in Bioinformatics, 18.1 (2017): 69-84.
 - Nov 2015 **Oliver Bonham-Carter and Dhundy Bastola**, "A text mining application for linking functionally stressed-proteins to their post-translational modifications", 2015 IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine (BIBM), IEEE, 2015.
 - July 2015 **Michael Camara, Oliver Bonham-Carter and Janyl Jumadinova**, "A Multi-Agent System with Reinforcement Learning Agents for Biomedical Text Mining", Proceedings of the 6th ACM Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology and Health Informatics (ACM-BCB), 2015.

- July 2014 Oliver Bonham-Carter, Jay Petersen and Dhundy Bastola, "A Content and Structural Assessment of Oxidative Motifs Across a Diverse Set of Life Forms", Computers in biology and medicine 53 (2014): 179-189.
- February 2014 **Oliver Bonham-Carter, Ishwor Thapa and Dhundy Bastola**, "Evidence of post translational modification bias extracted from the tRNA and corresponding amino acid interplay across a set of diverse organisms", IProceedings of the 5th ACM Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics (ACM-BCB), 2014.
 - July 2013 Oliver Bonham-Carter, Jay Pedersen, Lotfollah Najjar and Dhundy Bastola, "Modeling the Effects of Microgravity On Oxidation in Mitochondria: A Protein Damage Assessment Across a Diverse Set of Life Forms", 2013 IEEE 13th International Conference on Data Mining Workshops (DMBIH). IEEE, 2013.
 - July 2013 Oliver Bonham-Carter, Lotfollah Najjar and Dhundy Bastola, "Evidence of a Pathway of Reduction in Bacteria: Reduced Quantities of Restriction Sites Impact tRNA Activity in a Trial Set.", Proceedings of the International Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology and Biomedical Informatics, (ACM), 2013.
 - July 2013 Oliver Bonham-Carter, Abhishek Parakh and Dhundy Bastola, "sEncrypt: An Encryption Algorithm Inspired from Biological Processes", 12th IEEE International Conference on Trust, Security and Privacy in Computing and Communications (TrustCom), IEEE, 2013.
 - May 2013 **Oliver Bonham-Carter, Joe Steele and Dhundy Bastola**, "Alignment-free genetic sequence comparisons: a review of recent approaches by word analysis", Briefings in Bioinformatics, (2013): bbt052.
 - Nov 2012 **Oliver Bonham-Carter, Hesham Ali and Dhundy Bastola**, "A base composition analysis of natural patterns for the preprocessing of metagenome sequences", BMC Bioinformatics 14. Suppl 11 (2013): S5.
 - Nov 2012 Oliver Bonham-Carter, Hesham Ali and Dhundy Bastola, "A meta-genome sequencing and assembly preprocessing algorithm inspired by restriction site base composition", 2012 IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine Workshops (BIBMW), 2012.
 - May 2012 **Oliver Bonham-Carter, Lotfollah Najjar, Ishwor Thapa and Dhundy Bastola**, "Distributions of palindromic proportional content in bacteria", 8th International Symposium on Bioinformatics Research and Applications (ISBRA), 2012.
 - May 2001 Bruce M. Boman, Jeremy Z. Fields, Oliver Bonham-Carter and Olaf A. Runquist, "Computer modeling implicates stem cell overproduction in colon cancer initiation", Cancer research, 2001.

Selected Projects

GitHub Projects Portfolio, *Web:* https://github.com/obonhamcarter, An assortment of projects.

GradeAlert, A tool to help with reporting grades from CSV files for GitHub Classroom courses., GitHub clone link: git@github.com:developmentAC/gradeAlert.git, Web: https://github.com/developmentAC/gradeAlert.

Morse-Encode-Decoder. Α learning tool convert text to Morse Morse code code GitHub clone link: and to text., git@github.com:developmentAC/Morse-Encode-Decoder.git, Web: https: //github.com/developmentAC/Morse-Encode-Decoder.

GenExSt, A an method and tool to analyze normalized gene expression for cancer research. Topics keywords: Gene expression, normalization, cancer, GeneExSt, GitHub clone link: git@github.com:developmentAC/beagleTM.git, Web: https://github.com/developmentAC/genExSt.

BeagleTM, A text mining tool for developing visual and interactive relationship networks from PubMed article information. Topics keywords: PubMed, parsing, textmining, literature-review-tool, Beagletm, analysis, GitHub clone link: git@github.com:developmentAC/beagleTM.git, Web: https://github.com/developmentAC/beagleTM.

GatorShot, Web toy to superimpose the faculty photos from the Department of Computer Science at Allegheny College with your own live selfie. Topics include: webtoy, javascript, selfie, alleghenycollege, GitHub clone link: git@github.com:obonhamcarter/gatorShot.git, Web: https://github.com/obonhamcarter/gatorShot.

Selected Classes Taught

Academic Discource I, A class for success for incoming and first-year students.

Data Analytics for https://scholarly.co/, An online class about for the isolation and analysis of statistically-discovered trends and patterns from data sets. Includes material of ethics and responsibility in data science research..

Operating Systems, Programming skill, concepts and creation of algorithmic modules in the scope of computer operating systems. Topics include: CPU, memory access, memory pages, kernels, software launching and running and similar concepts.

Senior Thesis, First and /or second reader for senior comprehensive projects.

Data Analytics, Programming and analysis for the extraction of meaningful information from raw data using statistical models, programming and data science. Includes material of ethics and responsibility in data science research..

Bioinformatics, DNA, Protein sequence analysis, gene expression, proteomics, post-translational modifications and in relation to domains, etc.

Discrete Structures, Mathematics and programming, estimation, graph theory, probability statistics, numerical analysis, etc.

Databases, SQL schema design, programming syntax to store and extract data.

Junior Seminar, Theory, research and methods for success in CS careers.

Theory of Computing, Logic, turing machines, automata, designs of input-output control mechanisms.

Internship Seminar, A course designed to help students get into internships to allow them to gain experience and skill in their areas of Computer Science.

Selected Peer Review Service

- April 2022 **Briefings in Bioinformatics**.
- March 2022 **Briefings in Bioinformatics**.
 - July 2020 **SIGITE 2020**.
- February 2019 **Briefings in Bioinformatics**.
- December 2015 **Journal of Theoretical Biology**.
 - July 2014 ACM BCB 2014.
 - Jan 2015 Briefings in Bioinformatics.
 - May 2014 BMC.
 - January 2014 ECIS2014.
 - Sept 2013 **Briefings in Bioinformatics**.
 - July 2013 **Briefings in Bioinformatics**.
 - March 2013 SciVerse ScienceDirect.
 - February 2013 SciVerse ScienceDirect.
 - February 2013 **ECIS2013**.
- September 2012 **Briefings in Bioinformatics**.
 - August 2012 Briefings in Bioinformatics.
 - January 2012 **ECIS2012**.

Selected Community Service

- 2017 **QR** (Quantitative Reasoning) Tag creation committee, Creating a learning outcome rubric for the Quantitative Reasoning requirement, Allegheny College.
- 2017 **Young Student Outreach Teaching**, *Computer video game programming instruction*, Allegheny College.
- 2017 **26th Annual Sigma Xi Conference**, *Judge of undergraduate biology research*, Penn State Behrend, Held in Erie, PA.
- 2017 **Fourth Biannual Undergraduate Bioinformatics Education Conference**, *Presenter of bioinformatics teaching strategy for undergraduates*, St. Vincent College, Latrobe, PA.
- 2013-2016 **Volunteer bioinformatics workshop**, *Presenter of bioinformatics publications for undergraduates*, Omaha, Ne.
- 2013-2016 Volunteer bioinformatics workshop, Grade-school children's science, Omaha, Ne.
- 2012-2016 **Volunteer open house guide and presenter**, *University of Nebraska at Omaha*, Bioinformatics.
 - 2014 **Guest presenter and Speaker**, *Talk: Skills for success*, Given to new 2014 Ph.D. student class, University of Nebraska at Omaha.

- 2015 **Volunteer scout master**, *Tiger Scouts of America (Boy Scouts group)*, Group coordinator for Troup 244, Meadville, PA.
- Volunteer ICCS computer science conference, *University of Nebraska at Omaha*, Group coordinator.

Talks

March 2021 MozFest: Mozilla Festival: Responsible Computing Curricula – How do we do it? Info Link: https://schedule.mozillafestival.org/session/877N8H-1

Awards and Grants

- March 2021 **GRANT**: Principle Investigator for grant entitled, *Responsible Computer Science Challenge: Stage II* of the Mozilla Foundation. Award amount: \$64,000
- March 2019 **GRANT**: Principle Investigator for grant entitled, Responsible Computer Science Challenge: Stage I of the Mozilla Foundation. Award amount: \$144,000
- Janurary 2016 **AWARD**: Helen Hansen Outstanding Graduate Student Award, University of Nebraska at Omaha Award amount: \$500
- December 2015 **AWARD**: Dissertation Scholarship, University of Nebraska at Omaha Award amount: \$1,500
 - August 2015 **GRANT**: Recipient of the *NASA Nebraska Space Grant Fellowship*, NASA Nebraska Space Grant & EPSCoR, 6001 Dodge Street, CB 041, Omaha, NE 68182. Grant amount: \$5,000
 - June 2015 **AWARD**: Anjuman Ara Changez Award of Academic Achievement, University of Nebraska at Omaha Award amount: \$1,500
 - April 2015 AWARD: NASA recognition for research, Nebraska Academy of Science, Lincoln, NE
 - August 2014 **GRANT**: Recipient of the *NASA Nebraska Space Grant Fellowship*, NASA Nebraska Space Grant & EPSCoR, 6001 Dodge Street, CB 041, Omaha, NE 68182. Grant amount: \$5,000
 - April 2014 **AWARD**: First Place: *Best Paper*, Student Capstone Conference, College of Information Science and Technology, Peter Kiewit Institute, Omaha, Nebraska. Award amount: \$1,000
 - April 2014 **AWARD**: Second Place: Award of Excellence in Research, Student Capstone Conference, College of Information Science and Technology, Peter Kiewit Institute, Omaha, Nebraska. Award amount: \$500
 - April 2014 AWARD: NASA recognition for research, Nebraska Academy of Science, Lincoln, NE
 - July 2013 **GRANT**: Recipient of the *NASA Nebraska Space Grant Fellowship*, NASA Nebraska Space Grant & EPSCoR, 6001 Dodge Street, CB 041, Omaha, NE 68182. Grant amount: \$5,000
 - April 2013 **AWARD**: First Place: *Award of Excellence in Research*, Student Capstone Conference, College of Information Science and Technology, Peter Kiewit Institute, Omaha, Nebraska. Award amount: \$1,000

Memberships

2013 to Present IEEE: Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers

2013 to Present ACM: Association for Computing Machinery

2015 to Present Delta Epsilon lota: Academic Honor Society, University of Nebraska at Omaha Chapter

Education

2010 - 2016

Ph.D. in Information Technology - **Bioinformatics**, *University of Nebraska, PKI (UNO), Omaha, Bioinformatics*, Advisors: Dr. Dhundy (Kiran) Bastola and Dr. Hesham Ali.

Dissertation Thesis: "Patterns and Signals of Biology: An Emphasis On The Role of Post Translational Modifications in Proteomes for Function and Evolutionary Progression." University of Nebraska at Omaha, August 2016.

2007 - 2009

MS - **Mathematics**, University of Nebraska (UNO), Omaha, Mathematics with applications in Bioinformatics/Mathematical Biology.

Undergraduate Mathematics Course Work, *University of Nebraska, Omaha, Preparation for Masters graduate school.*

Undergraduate Mathematics Course Work, Conservatoire National des Arts et Métiers, Paris, France, General Mathematics with applications in Science.

English Technical Writing Workshop, Creighton University.

French Cultural Studies, *Université de La Sorbonne, Paris, France*, Diplômé: *La Civilisation Française: French Linguistics, Culture and Literature*.

BS - **Biology**, Creighton University, Omaha, Biology, biostatistics, and Biochemistry. **Diplomé**, Université Stendhal-Grenoble 3, "Perfection of Oral French" and "Perfection of Written French".

Languages

English

Maternal

French

Fluent (Ô, Mais oui!)

Computer Skills/Software

OS: Linux, Mac, Windows

Web HUGO, Jekyll, JavaScript, HTML, page layout

development:

General: Git and GitHub programming, OpenOffice

Programming: Python, JavaScript, C/C++, Java, LATEX, R-statistic, GoLang

Graphics: DALL-E, GIMP, PhotoShop, Krita, Inkscape, lender, Creation via www.canva.com

Cloud Docker, Kubernetes, AWS, VPN's, cloud computing setup and operations

Computing:

Video: OBS, OpensShot, green screening, microphone adjustment, video recording, YouTube

video channel growing

Mathematical: Maple, Mathematica, R-Statistic, SPSS, Octave, MatLab

Interests

Research Academic research in Bioinformatics: text mining, gene expression correlation in disease, data

analytics at large-scale and Analysis by methods of Information Theory

Biking Long biking trips are exciting.

Tennis My game still needs some work...

Physical Most of my favorite classes, books and trips to museums have been to learn about science.

Sciences

Using plastics Negative: No plastics, please.